<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe relation, of what is hapned since the last of August 1598. by comming of the Spanish campe into the dukedom of Cleue: and the bordering free countries, which with most odious and barbarous crueltie they take as enemies, for the seruice of God, and the King of Spaine (as they say). Heerunto is adioyned a translation out of Latin, of a letter of the Emperours embassadour, to the admirant of Arragon, the generall of the said army: with his answere. Together with a description of the vvhale of Berckhey, or the great fish which stranded or came on shoare at Berckhey in Holland, the third of February 1598. ... Also a letter of the Emperour of Germany, to the admirant of Arragon ... With the admirants answere. ... Faithfully translated out of the Dutch coppy printed at Roterdam.</title>
            <title>Walvisch van Berkhey. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10588</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20861</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115784</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851002</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851002</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16254</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10588)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16254)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 351:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe relation, of what is hapned since the last of August 1598. by comming of the Spanish campe into the dukedom of Cleue: and the bordering free countries, which with most odious and barbarous crueltie they take as enemies, for the seruice of God, and the King of Spaine (as they say). Heerunto is adioyned a translation out of Latin, of a letter of the Emperours embassadour, to the admirant of Arragon, the generall of the said army: with his answere. Together with a description of the vvhale of Berckhey, or the great fish which stranded or came on shoare at Berckhey in Holland, the third of February 1598. ... Also a letter of the Emperour of Germany, to the admirant of Arragon ... With the admirants answere. ... Faithfully translated out of the Dutch coppy printed at Roterdam.</title>
                  <title>Walvisch van Berkhey. English.</title>
                  <author>Rudolf II, Holy Roman Emperor, 1552-1612.</author>
                  <author>Mendoza, Francisco de, 1549-1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28; [2], 13, [1] p., folded plate : map  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [Edward Allde for] Iohn VVolfe, and are to be solde at his shop in Popes head Alley, neere vnto the Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Walvisch van Berkhey.</note>
                  <note>Actual printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>"The letter of the Emperour of Germanie, to the admirant of Arragon" has separate dated title page, pagination, and register.</note>
                  <note>The map has letterpress title: The scituation of the lands of Cleue and Munster, where the Spanish forces now are.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whales --  Holland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Germany --  History --  Rudolf II, 1576-1612 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16254:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16254:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A briefe relation, of what is hapned ſince the</hi> laſt of Auguſt 1598. by comming of the Spaniſh campe into the Dukedome of <hi>Cleue:</hi> and the bordering free Countries, which with moſt odious and barbarous crueltie they take as enemies, for the ſeruice of God, and the King of Spaine (as they ſay.)</p>
            <p>Heereunto is adioyned a Tranſlation out of Latin, of a Letter of the Emperours Embaſſadour, to the Admirant of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon,</hi> the Generall of the ſaid Army: With his anſwere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with a deſcription of the VVhale of Berckhey,</hi> or the great fiſh which ſtranded or came on ſhoare at <hi>Berckhey</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> the third of February 1598. With anotation therupon.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Letter of the Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirant of <hi>Arragon,</hi> Generall for the Archeduke <hi>Albertus,</hi> in the Countries of <hi>Cleue</hi> and <hi>Munſter,</hi> &amp;c. With the Admirants anſwere.</p>
            <p>The conſpiracy of the three Biſhops.</p>
            <p>The death of the Earle of Brooke.</p>
            <p>The Admirants Letter to the Counſaile of <hi>Gulich</hi> touching the death of the ſaid Earle.</p>
            <p>The liſt of the Souldiers leuied by the Proteſtant Princes of <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully tranſlated out of the Dutch coppy Printed at</hi> Roterdam.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Iohn VVolfe,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in Popes head Alley, neere vnto the Exchange. 1599.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:16254:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16254:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſcituation of the lands of</hi> Cleue <hi>and</hi> Munſter, Where the Spanish forces now are.</head>
                  <figDesc>map of Cleve and Munster, illustration of a whale.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16254:3"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16254:3"/>
                  <head>A breefe relation of what is happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſince the laſt of Auguſt <hi>1598.</hi> by the comming of the Spanish campe into the Countries of <hi>Cleeue,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>On Franciſco de Mendoſſa, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante d'Arragon, &amp;c.</hi> Generall with Earle <hi>Frederick van den Berge,</hi> as Marſhall of the campe belonging to the Archeduke <hi>Albert,</hi> in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b. laſt, <hi>An.</hi> 1598. came to the Riuer of <hi>Rhine,</hi> at <hi>Orſoy,</hi> with 62. Enſignes of Spaniards, 19. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of Italians, 2. Enſignes of Iriſhmen, 4. regiments of Wallons, containing 43. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, 4. regiments of Germaines of 42. Enſignes, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with 168. Enſignes of footemen, which in all is eſteemed to be 22. thouſand footemen, with 2. thouſand horſe comprehended in 28. companies, aſwell Spaniards, Italians, Netherlanders, and others: with theſe troopes the aforeſaid Admirant, deſired to be let into the little cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Orſoy</hi> ſcituated vpon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> a mile aboue <hi>Berck,</hi> &amp; being by the Marſhall of <hi>Cleue</hi> (who proteſted as Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trall) denied, he began to ſeale the cittie,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Orſoy</hi> taken.</note> which the Citti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens perceiuing, being affraide, let his people in, vppon promiſe, of onely paſſing the <hi>Rhine.</hi> But he forgetting his promiſe, began to ſtrengthen the cittie, and cauſed 10. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of Wallons, and 3. regiments of Spaniards, with 12. companies of Horſemen, to be paſſed ouer the <hi>Rhine,</hi>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:16254:4"/>
and ouer againſt <hi>Orſoy</hi> at <hi>Walſem,</hi> he cauſed a ſtrong Sconce to be made. Vpon the Caſtell of <hi>Orſoy</hi> laye ſome Souldiours belonging to the Prince of <hi>Cleue,</hi> to the which the Admirant went himſelfe in perſon, with thrée Fryars and a hangman, hauing many halters in his hand, with which he threatned the Souldiours, that if they would not deliuer vp the Caſtell, they might confeſſe themſelues, for that there was a hangman ready to hang them,<note place="margin">The Caſtell ſummoned and yeelded.</note> ſo that the Souldiours were forced to yéelde the ſame vp vnto him: alſo all other Forts and Citties thereabout he cauſed to be ſummoned, taken, pilled and ranſomed, not fauouring the citties of <hi>Alpen</hi> and <hi>Meurs,</hi> which had obtained a letter from <hi>Albertus,</hi> that they might remaine as Neutrals.</p>
                  <p>By letters written out of the Campe, was vnderſtood that the Admirant had taken <hi>Orſoy</hi> the 10. of September, with intent to remaine there, &amp; to ſtrengthen the ſame on both ſides of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> before that he would attempt any thing elſe. The Campe did as then nothing elſe but ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runne, and robbe the land of <hi>Cleue</hi> as enemies: by ſome priſoners was vnderſtood that they meant to winter in the Neutrall Citties, to ſpare the <hi>Brabanders</hi> and <hi>Flem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings,</hi> that the Souldiours daylye by wante of money runne away. That the heads in the campe were different. Earle <hi>Frederick</hi> counſelled to go towards <hi>Ouer-ryſſell,</hi> but the Admirant would paſſe downe alongſt the <hi>Rhine.</hi> The Cittizens of <hi>Orſey,</hi> made pittifull moanes and requeſts to their Lord the Duke of <hi>Cleue,</hi> to obtaine of the Admirant that with wife and children they might peaceably depart, leauing all their goods and wealth behinde them, for they were by the Spaniards forced to worke like ſlaues.</p>
                  <p>The 25. of September, the cittizens and chéefe in <hi>Cleue</hi> land, concluded that the redeliuery of <hi>Orſoy</hi> ſhould with all diligence be procured, and that if in caſe the Admirant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to doe it, that as then with all expedition, meanes ſhould be ſought to leuie men, for the defence of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, which of many was little eſtéemed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16254:4"/>The laſt of September, the<note n="*" place="margin">The cheefe Counſellors and officers touching mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall cauſes.</note> 
                     <hi>Creyts,</hi> at <hi>Dormont</hi> being aſſembled, concluded to ſend the Earle of <hi>Lippe</hi> to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirant to procure the rendring of <hi>Orſoy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There was great want of money and victuals in the Campe, for the Country aboue fiue miles round of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey</hi> was deſtroyed, inſomuch that the ſouldiers ran away in great number, as well Spaniards as other.</p>
                  <p>The ſixt of October, ſome part of the Campe departed to the Caſtle of the Earle of <hi>Brooke,</hi> ſituate on the Roer, who notwithſtanding that he ſhewed all good neutrality and that he defended his libertie they forcibly beſiedged, beſhot, tooke and pilled (as enemies) his Caſtle, and place of reſidence or dwelling, his wife and children they conueyed to a monaſtery: the Souldiers of <hi>Cleue</hi> &amp; <hi>Berge,</hi> with the houſe-kéepers, which were flee into the Caſtle, contrary to their promiſe and agréement, they flew in the fielde, after they were with theyr conſents departed from the Caſtle. The Earle himſelfe they vſed as a criminall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, &amp; notwithſtanding that he anſwered himſelfe as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Noble man belonging to the Empire, and appealed therupon, &amp; that he had yéelded vp the Caſtle vpon conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of life, lands &amp; goods ſaued, for himſelf and thoſe which were with him vpon theſame:<note place="margin">The Lorde of Herdenbergh with a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher murdred in the Caſtell.</note> they forced him to goe to Maſſe, and as they fell in diſputation thereabout, they there ſlewe his Nephew the Lorde of <hi>Herdenbergh</hi> wyth a Preacher.</p>
                  <p>This Caſtle of <hi>Brooke</hi> being thus as enemy taken, without in any ſorte reſpecting their promiſe, that it was yéelded vpon condition of life and goods ſaued. The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirant of <hi>Arragon, Don Franciſco de mendoſſa,</hi> durſt well defend the ſame to the Counſaile of <hi>Cleue,</hi> that it ought not to be badly taken what his men did, that there was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion giuen: And that thoſe of <hi>Cleue</hi> and <hi>Berge</hi> ought not to reuenge all what happeneth, but ought much rather to haue pacience, in hope of a good ende of thoſe miſeries, which now they endured through néede, for the common good,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16254:5"/>
and that there ought no enmity to be ſhewed, to the end not to bring themſelues in the danger of the furious and bitter armes of the angred Souldiers, which were thereby moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Moreouer the Ieſuits make themſelues heard, that thoſe which reſiſt them, doe make themſelues ſubiect to the cruell puniſhment, and that they are rewarded according to their merits, and that they haue puniſhed them to the example of the others, to the ende that none ſhould doe ſo any more, but holde themſelues in dutifull obedience, and forberance in this eſpeciall néed.</p>
                  <p>The eleuenth of October when this hapned, the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſet ſome number of men to <hi>Buricke</hi> ſituated on the <hi>Rhyne</hi> beneath <hi>Bercke</hi> ouer againſt <hi>Weſell:</hi> the Cittizens being Neutrals refuſed to yéeld vp theyr Citty, but ſéeing that they would force them, were conſtrayned to yéeld, and were thereby ouercharged with great numbers of ſouldiers.</p>
                  <p>On the ſame day happened the moſt deteſtable murder, of the Earle of <hi>Brooke,</hi> after he was riſen from the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the euening,<note place="margin">The Earle of <hi>Brooke</hi> mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered.</note> and walking in the Court of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, there came two Souldiers of the Gariſon to him; aſk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him if he would walke into the Garden, whereto he condiſcending they went out of the Caſtle Gate thorough the Garden, towards the Water mill, where one of the ſouldiers at vnawares, gaue the Earle a great blow, with a halfe Pike vpon the head that he felled him, the Earle crying O Ieſu: which done he drew out his ſwoord and thruſt it through him, whereat hee cryed once againe O Ieſu. One of the Earles ſeruantes being by, ranne away and leaping downe into the mill-damme ſaued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>The fourtéenth of October the Duke of <hi>Cleue</hi> ſent his deputy to the Campe of the Count <hi>Maurice,</hi> Counſaile of State, and of the warre, proteſting that all what the Admirant did to them, did not happen by any conſent of the countrey, but by méete force, and againſt his will and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16254:5"/>
the countrie. This yet notwithſtanding the opinion in the vnited prouinces was, that the Spaniard would not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt thoſe things in the land of <hi>Cleue,</hi> without the expres conſent of the emperor, according to the Admirants charge giuen him by the king of Spaine, and the Archeduke <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus,</hi> and confirmed by the Emperour in <hi>Anno</hi> 1596. who then willed him to that end to haue his forces ready, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ought well ſéeke to get all the land of <hi>Cleue</hi> into their hands, and to holde the ſame, with the Prince thereof, in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardſhip, and ſo to aſſure themſelues, the lands ſhould not fall into the hands of the Princes of <hi>Brandenborgh</hi> &amp; <hi>Swez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brugh,</hi> the which by right of marriage might pretend to be the néereſt heyres, all which, thoſe of <hi>Spaine</hi> &amp; <hi>Auſtria</hi> would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hinder, becauſe they are of the reformed religion, and might in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>re to the vnited prouinces. Of theſe and ſuch like complots, the vnited Prouinces haue diuers times ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed the Counſell of <hi>Cleue,</hi> and to preuent theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plots, they had alſo proffered to make certaine agréements to the fréeing of the riuer of <hi>Rhine,</hi> and as then thereby to haue withſtood theſe inuaſions, but it was at that time not eſtéemed nor beléeued.</p>
                  <p>This common opinion was in a moment more and more ſpread abroade and confirmed in the thoughts of ſearching ſpirits, becauſe that newes came, that the citties of <hi>Diuxla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> and <hi>Holt</hi> were likewiſe taken, together with <hi>Eſſen Wynendall,</hi> and the Forte or houſe of <hi>Hullen,</hi> vſing them moſt odiouſlie, killing and murdering all thoſe which they knew to be of the reformed religion, &amp; enemies to their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes: alſo they broake the new Neutrality which was granted to <hi>Meurs,</hi> &amp; lodged 8. companies of Horſmen therin.</p>
                  <p>The Admirant alſo beſought the citty of <hi>Bockholt,</hi> that he might lay 500. horſe in their cittie, and to thoſe of <hi>Borc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kum</hi> 300. horſe.</p>
                  <p>He alſo beſought thoſe of <hi>Weſel</hi> to take in 2000. footmen of his, and 1000. horſe: or elſe that they ſhould make vp 200. thouſand Crownes, and a monthes breade for his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16254:6"/>
Campe, and to deliuer hoſtages at <hi>Burick,</hi> that the Count <hi>Maurice</hi> ſhould attempt nothing about <hi>Weſſell</hi> and <hi>Lippe,</hi> with many other ſuch vnſéemely and ſhamefull demaunds and fearefull threates: vaunting himſelfe of the facte of the Earle of <hi>Brooke,</hi> threatning to vſe all other in like ſorte: yea to vſe the Earle of <hi>Lippe,</hi> no leſſe then the Earle of <hi>Brooke,</hi> and that therefore, they ſhould not truſt vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ayde, for that there was none in the Dutch nation which ſhould dare to touch him. The cittizens of <hi>Weſſell</hi> being in great feare and diſtreſſe were forced vpon the 22. of October, to come to an agréement, that they ſhould giue for their citty, and the citty of <hi>Rees,</hi> 150. thouſand Gilders, and a thouſand meaſures of Rye, and cauſed a Bridge, to be made ouer the <hi>Lippe</hi> which was accordingly effected vpon the 23. of October. Thoſe of <hi>Santen</hi> promiſed 18. thouſand Gilders, and other places more.</p>
                  <p>With this money he paide his men which had long cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for money, and paſſed the <hi>Lippe,</hi> and ſent all about the citties of <hi>Munſter</hi> for money: Alſo they raunſomed many Gentlemens houſes, many whereof they moſte wickedly ranſacked and pilled. They alſo robbed the villages of <hi>Winterſwicke</hi> and <hi>Alten</hi> &amp;c. commaunding thoſe of <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merick</hi> to make a bridge ouer the Water of <hi>Hetter.</hi> Alſo hee ſent ſome men with Ordinaunce towardes <hi>Rees,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding the citty for a time to lay his men in, vpon their refuſall he cauſed more Ordinance to be brought to it, and ſo feared the citty,<note place="margin">Rees taken.</note> that they were forced to yéeld it vp to him, without any reſpit of an houre, to aſſemble their cittizens: and laide in the ſame citty to the coſtes of the cittizens 8. Enſignes, he alſo tooke all the Caſtles there abouts.</p>
                  <p>Vpon the ſecond of Nouember, the Admirant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded paſſage for his Ordinaunce through <hi>Emmerick</hi> by which meanes he made himſelfe maſter of the citty and leauing a great number of men therein, departed with his campe to <hi>Elton.</hi> Alſo hee tooke <hi>Yſelborgh</hi> where many
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16254:6"/>
cittizens were wickedly murthered. The Prince of <hi>Cleue</hi> had his Embaſſadour by the Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought the Duke to write to the Admirant and to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent at <hi>Bruſſell,</hi> that the countrie might be fréed from this trouble. Alſo he vndertooke to mooue the King of France (the land of <hi>Cleue</hi> being concluded in the peace) to that end to ſend to <hi>Bruſſell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <head>A copie of the Letter which the <hi>Emperours Legat wrote to</hi> the Admirant.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Lluſtrious and worthy Prince, it is knowne aſwell to your excellencie, as to me, what at two ſeuerall times hath béene betwéene vs done and effected: Firſt in the cittie of <hi>Gelder,</hi> when your excellencie firſt approached theſe countries with your campe: and afterwards, when by charge and commaundement of his Emperiall maieſtie, I treated about the mariage of the illuſtrious prince of <hi>Cleue, Gulich</hi> &amp; <hi>Berge,</hi> with the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> I haue declared, that the ſaid illuſtrious duke of <hi>Cleue,</hi> is very badly, &amp; vnreaſonably dealt withall. The citty of <hi>Orſoy</hi> being forcibly taken from him, and the kings ſouldiours run vnbridled, vſing all manner of cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in murthering, ſpoiling, &amp; burning, as enemies and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, not fauoring the liues nor goods of many. And where before I ſtedfaſtly beléeued, that a Prince (whoſe worde ought to be ſure) and had by ſo many promiſes bound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, would be found true, as concerning that the cittie of <hi>Orſoy</hi> ſhould within <hi>10.</hi> or at furtheſt within <hi>20</hi> dayes, be diſcharged of thoſe expences, and redeliuered.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="8" facs="tcp:16254:7"/>Item that the Campe ſhould bee remooued out of theſe Neutral lands, as ſoone as <hi>Berke</hi> ſhuld be rendred. And the more did I beléeue that this ſhould haue béen fully accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, becauſe that the ſame hath at diuers times bin pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and confirmed, by worde and ſealed letters to the Illuſtrous Prince of <hi>Cleue</hi> and his ſiſter. I now finde my ſelfe greatly deceiued, ſith I perceiue nothing but break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of promiſes and néedleſſe delaies, yea more, there is nothing followed vpon the promiſes, but foe-like enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, and the iuſt contrariety of the ſaid promiſes. For being departed I haue vnderſtood, how the one Citty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the other hath béen forcibly taken, and others conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to paye great ſummes of moneys and quantities of corne: all the which comming to the Court I found to be true: and more ouer heare and ſée ſome Citties taken, and other ſome with great cruelty forced to pay great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions. Any one, who willingly would haue his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try fréed from ſuch troubles may eaſily iudge howe the Emperour (in whoſe behalfe I am héere appointed, to take care for the country and the Prince thereof) with all the other Germaine Princes: yea all other Princes of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, will be mooued at the report hereof, for this is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which toucheth them in generall. The houſe of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayne</hi> ſhall by this marriage be ioyned and bound to that of <hi>Cleue:</hi> alſo the houſe of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> ſhall by a new brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood be knit to the King of <hi>France.</hi> And many Princes, doe belong to this houſe aſwell by bloud as mariage.</p>
                        <p>Therefore one ought to take care, that all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be not vexed nor vrged by the great diſhonour and ſhame which is done them, and ſo to renue and teare vp the olde wound, which is yet ſcarce whole, which I wiſhe his Catholique Maieſty, (as being one of his welwillers) to looke vnto.</p>
                        <p>Where are there any ſo vnwiſe and vnexperienced that vnderſtand not, that it greatly hindreth and diſturbeth the ſeruice of God, that a Catholique Prince, who hath with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16254:7"/>
ſuch zeale and innumerable charges defended and vphelde the Catholique religion in the middeſt of the ſtreames and ſtormes of hereſie, ſhould bee thus ſuppreſſed and ſpoiled, and his kindred be diſpiſed? That leauing the enemy vnaſſaulted, the whole power of the warre with the worſt and baſeſt raſcals that can be found in the world, ſhall be bent againſt the Kings couzens and bloud kindred. That the Churches ſhoulde bée pylled, and the Moneſtaryes robbed: the ſpirituall men thruſt away and beaten. The young Virgins (deuoted to God) rauiſhed, and all holines tredden vnderfoote.</p>
                        <p>Alſo that the Embaſſadour (which among the heathens are frée) are with publique force apprehended, as is hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to my owne perſon, and the Embaſſadours of other Princes, ſome daies paſt when I came by water to <hi>Cleue.</hi> Where can any one (I ſay) be found ſo ſimple and ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, that doeth not perceiue and marke, that this ſtretcheth to the diſpiſing and hindraunce of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
                        <p>Beſides, that which is greatly to be doubted, that is that the honour of the renouned houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> will be diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of euery man, the which vntill nowe for their iuſtice, and kindneſſe, the ſimplicity of their enterpriſes, and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable déeds, hath béen fauoured ouer all, as alſo, becauſe they haue alwaies wiſely ſhunned, the ſuſpition, of friends or foes, of bearing armes in any wrongefull warres: yea it is to be ſuſpected, that the Catholique Kinge, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther raiſers and authors of thoſe cruelties, ſhalbe by God moſt iuſtly puniſhed, the guiltleſſe bloud which they ſpyll. crying for reuenge. For (O beloued) what proſperity are thoſe to expect which themſelues fauour nothing, nor leaue nothing vnſpoiled: which lay their hands vpon (and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt) their kindred as ſtraungers, their friendes as enemies, the worthy as malefactors, and the guiltleſſe as the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie?</p>
                        <p>I am forced by my office to aduertiſe his imperial maieſty
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16254:8"/>
of theſe bloodie tyrannies, euen in a rowe as they are hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened. I admoniſh and earneſtly pray your honour, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt from vſing of violence henceforward, but to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to giue and render againe to the hands of the illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince of <hi>Cleue,</hi> his taken Citties, Caſtels, and forts, to tranſport your Armie for ſome other continent, to make amends and reſtitution of the damages doone, and to giue no occaſion of further diſpleaſure or diſcommoditie. All the which although it were, lawfull, iuſt, lawdable and beſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to a Prince, yet will I by the bearer héereof, expect a reaſonable and diſcréete anſwer, I commit your Honor to the protection of God. </p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>From <hi>Cleue</hi> 
                              <date>the laſt of October, <hi>1598.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline> 
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Vnderſtood. <hi>Carolus Sonderpuhill, Legat of his Imperiall Maieſtie.</hi>
                              </hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Author.</note>In ſooth, I beléeue that this Embaſſador meanes well enough, and would willing ſee the Carte goe vpright, but his Lorde and maiſter is not of that minde. For were it otherwiſe, and that he were diſpleaſed therewith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dooth he not deale earneſtly with his brother <hi>Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus?</hi> who muſt confeſſe to haue giuen his Lieutenant the Admirant commiſſion and charge, to take the citties of <hi>Cleue,</hi> to robbe them, and murther the people by multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, &amp;c. Or he muſt ſay, that the Admirant had doone all without his conſent and commaundement, and of <hi>propria authoritate:</hi> Hath he then doone this without commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement? he ought then to puniſh him well for it, and to ſet the citties of <hi>Cleue</hi> and <hi>Munſter</hi> in their fréedome againe, and to recompence their damages. But it appeareth daily more and more, that the court of Spaine, the Emperor and his brethren, as alſo the Pope, are well agreed, &amp; that all is but diſſimulation, they faining to be diſpleaſed with the things whereof they are cauſers. I will therfore to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and ſeruice of the Reader, yet ioyne heereto the copie of the Admirants anſwere.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16254:8"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>Superſcription.</hi> To the Noble and worthie Lord, <hi>Carolus Sonderpuhill,</hi> Knight of Ieruſalem, Counſellor and Legat of the Emperour: my eſpeciall goodfriend.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble and Worthy Lorde, wee haue with all reuerence the ſeuentéenth of Nouember, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued your honors Letters, dated the laſt of Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober, wee haue alſo vnderſtood each point of the ſame. Firſt we commend and praiſe your honors ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice &amp; care, in the executing of the commaundement of his imperiall maieſty, touching the encreaſing of the honour and welfare, of the Illuſtrous Prince of <hi>Cleue,</hi> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his countries and ſubiects. Your honor ſéemes at this preſent iuſtly diſpleaſed, by reaſon of many faults and miſdemeanors, which (being firſt beheld and not ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grounded) would greatly agrauate the Kings campe and vs, except that from the beginning and firſt enterpriſe, the cauſe could be prooued, that thoſe which are accuſed ſhould haue ſought and procured, miſerie and calamitie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéed of helpe and counſaile, inſomuch that theſe troubles muſt be moderately applyed to the circumſtance of the matter and cauſe, of the time, of the place, and neceſſity. I wiſh that your honour were well informed of the eſtate of this matter, and of the right wherewith his royall Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty maketh thoſe warres, of the méekeneſſe which is vſed therein: as alſo of the good affection and ſeruice of his roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Maieſty, and the Eſtate of the Empire, together with their iudgement of the cruell tyrany of the obſtinate. Item of the neceſſity of this enterpriſe, and the things which are hapned: as of néedfull maintenance, the ſcituation of the places of the illuſtrous Prince of <hi>Gulich,</hi> the neceſſity in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>, according to the oportunities of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16254:9"/>
the warres: Item of the good déeds of his royall Maieſtie, and of his true affection, as alſo of the moſt illuſtrous Prince of <hi>Gulion,</hi> and the whole Empire. Of all which, and many other cauſes, if that your honour were fully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the truthe informed (which we hope ſhall ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye happen) we doubt not in the leaſt, but that your honor would as fréely and willingly as other, vnderſtand the whole reaſon and diſpoſition héereof, imputing the faulte of the trouble to the authours, and wholy excuſe his royall Maieſtie, yea and haue compaſſion of them, ſince that for their great and laudable déeds, they are vnreaſonablie and falſlie belyed and blamed. Your honour ſhould alſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret for the beſt, excuſe and defend our déedes, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and care, before the Prince and his ſubiects, in reſpect of the furthering of the diſcipline, and the patience of the vneaſe which we endure, by reaſon of the greatneſſe of the campe, and the differing of payes. Alſo your honour could double the ſeruice ſhewed vnto the illuſtrious. Duke of <hi>Lorraine</hi> and other Princes, and dayly with all dilligence and care, hinder the feare of the difficultie, and vn eaſe of the French Kings ſide, who is to be feared in the Empire, and will not ſéeke the aduauncement of the Prince of <hi>Cleue.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Your Honor ſhould alſo mooue his emperiall maieſtie, and the eſtates of the Empire, to the ioyning in this war, againſt the common perrill of Chriſtendome, to wit, againſt the cauſers of this great miſchiefe. But this all ſhall more manifeſtly, by the déede and experience of the matter, as alſo of the royall Maieſtie, and the illuſtrious Archeduke <hi>Albert,</hi> and our care, together with the eſtates of the Empire and other Princes, he brought to light, we eſteeme according to the oportunitie of the time, to haue ſufficientlie ſatiſfied the illuſtrious Prince of <hi>Cleue, Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lich, &amp;c.</hi> by our laſt letter, which alſo we did imparte to your honour, and alſo eſteeme that they ought by the ſame to be found good: what toucheth the reſt, I beſeeche
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16254:9"/>
your honor, by the loue and goodwill which you beare, to his emperiall Maieſty, to his royall Maieſty, to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke <hi>Albertus,</hi> and the Illuſtrous Prince of <hi>Gulich</hi> (which by fraternity are bound together) as alſo by the loue which your honour beares to the preſeruation of the Catholique religion, yea whole Chriſtendome, to continue conſtantly in the good affection and reaſon, as your honor hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy begun, to be ayding with his counſaile and déedes to the common cauſes and vs, and to guide and gouerne the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with the illuſtrious Prince and his counſaile accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your wiſedome. We beſéech God to graunt your honor health, conſtancy, mercy and ſtrength, to finiſh ſuch a holy péece of worke.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>From the campe before <hi>Deutecum</hi> 
                              <date>the <hi>12.</hi> of Nouember. <hi>1598.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Vnderſtood. Your honors wholy deuoted. <hi>Don Franciſco de Mendoſſa,</hi> Great Admirant of the Realme of <hi>Arragon,</hi> Marqueſſe of <hi>Quadelles, de Valde penas,</hi> of the Stately Calatrononian order, Steward of the Catholique King, as alſo Counſelour at Standes, and of the Martiall affaires, chiefe Steward in the Court of the moſt Illuſtrous Archeduke <hi>Albertus:</hi> And Captaine Generall of the Carrabins.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>IS not this an euident and reaſonable anſwere, iuſtly might wee euery where bée exclaimed on, and called barbarous and baſtardes, not worthy of the name of Netherlands, if wee ſhould reſigne to the Spaniardes (whereof the moſte parte are but Baptiſed Iewes) our right and fréedome, which to mayntaine, ſo many thouſandes of vertuous men haue loſte theyr lyues,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16254:10"/>
and the earth béen dyed with their bloud, haue we no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on our ſelues? let vs call to minde the miſerie which our wiues and children are to expect, if that we be maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Spaniards, eyther by force, or their deceiptfull treatiſe of peace. Wee are bound to take care for them, ſince they themſelues haue not the wit: Let vs then make it appeare that there is yet a valliant Lyons heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Netherlands, for the preſeruation of the true Catholique Religion, or priuiledges and fréedomes, and for the turning off of ſlauery and ſeruitude.</p>
                  <p>Vpon the 7. of Nouember the Admirant aſſaulted the Towne of <hi>Deutecum</hi> in the County of <hi>Zutphen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deutecum taken.</note> and by appointment the Souldiers departed it with their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, he marched forwards towards the Forte of <hi>Scuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenburch,</hi> ſcituated in a bogge, which hee alſo tooke. The Admirant hauing want of all things, durſt not aduenture any further: For being that he had denyed ſafegard to the Country people or Boores of the County of <hi>Zutphen,</hi> to dwell quietly, but allowed them time and leaſure, to flye with their corne and cattle into the ſtronge Citties: hee found no victuals for his Campe, and were forced in ſtéed of bread to eate Colwort-ſtalkes, clodded bloud of beaſtes, and what els they could get.</p>
                  <p>About this time there was an aſſembly in the Cittie of <hi>Dortmont,</hi> of the Deputies of the Princes and Lords, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Weſtphalian Creyts,</hi> whereof the Chiefe is the Earle of <hi>Lippe,</hi> whether all the complaintes of the Neighbour countries were brought. In which aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly was reſolued, to write Letters on the 13. of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to the Emperour, and to the foure Princes Electors, of the <hi>Rhyne,</hi> that they alſo might write to the Emperour, and to the Admirant, and at <hi>Bruſſell</hi> to the Cardinall <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> Gouernour of the Netherlands. Appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to méete againe at <hi>Collin</hi> in Ianuarie.</p>
                  <p>When the Admirant, by the reſiſtance of Count <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice,</hi> and the Campe of the vnited Prouinces, had béen for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16254:10"/>
to retyre. Fearing want of victuals and other neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, he departed the 16. of Nouember for the Biſhopricke of <hi>Munſter,</hi> leauing fiue Enſignes at <hi>Deutecum,</hi> with a Banner of Horſemen of <hi>Mendo</hi> a Spaniard.</p>
                  <p>The Earle <hi>Fredricke</hi> tooke <hi>Bockholt,</hi> and alſo <hi>Borcken,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bockholt and Borckentaken.</note> where they dealt very badly with the Cittizens. From thence they departed for <hi>Schermbacke</hi> and other places as <hi>Dortmont, Eſſen, Dorſten,</hi> which they ſhot at, <hi>Coeſuelt, Steenwort, Rekelinckhueſen,</hi> and many Gentlemens hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. They were alſo twice before <hi>Ooſtdorp,</hi> but were faine to retyre: thoſe of <hi>Ham</hi> reſiſted them alſo valiantly. They threatned the Biſhopricke and county of <hi>Oſnaburgh</hi> with fire, demaunding an hundred thouſand Dollars, but it was denyed, and they tooke Souldiers to them. <hi>Barlote</hi> was ſent to <hi>Emmerick,</hi> where on the 23. of Nouember he would with more men bee let in: but being that there were thrée Enſignes belonging to the Earle of <hi>Bye,</hi> the Cittizens with their (forced) helpe, held <hi>Barlote</hi> out. Who thereat greatly ſpyted at his departure from thence, threatned the Citty greatly. To excuſe this refuſall there was ſent the Deacon with certaine of her perſons to the Admirant, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring that Neutrality had been graunted them, and that there was no reaſon the ſame ſhould be broken. The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirant gaue for anſwere, that the time, the ſeruice of God and the King required ſuch, and therewith they ought to haue patience: Whereupon the Deacon replyed that it would be a great ſhame and reproach before God and the world, and to the name of the Catholique Spaniards, that all promiſes and contents may bee broken and anſwered with the ſeruice of God and the King,<note place="margin">The Admirant is by the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for being an vpholder of Ieſuits, in brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his word and promiſe.</note> and with the eſtate of matters, which things the Turkes and Moores did not do. And ſo doing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was no maruaile, though the vnited Prouinces would not truſt to any peace, ſince that neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors and friends are ſo dealt withall. The Admirant was greatly enraged and aſhamed at theſe words, ſending the Embaſſadors away, but not without peril of their perſons</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:16254:11"/>Shortly after the tenth of December the Spaniſh Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons were forced to abandon <hi>Emmericke</hi> by the Count <hi>Maurice</hi> with the Army of the vnited Prouinces, where the Admirant laye at <hi>Rees</hi> with thrée thouſand men, and <hi>Barlot</hi> at <hi>Doornicke,</hi> and diuers other there abouts, and could not hinder the ſame. For on the 4. of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſome of the Count <hi>Maurice</hi> his men marched vp aboue <hi>Rees,</hi> and thruſt the ditches through, which notwithſtanding were guarded by ſouldiers, they ſcarce being able to ſaue themſelues from the water, and were faine to bee carried in boates out of the houſes wherein they had hidden themſelues: and <hi>Emmericke</hi> was ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured to kéepe themſelues Neutrall, taking in ſome of their Princes ſouldiers for their defence.</p>
                  <p>In this ſort the Spaniſh Campe forced the Citties of the Biſhopricke of <hi>Munſter,</hi> to take in their Garriſon, alſo the Biſhopricke of <hi>Eſſen</hi> ouerrunning the houſes and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles belonging to the Earle of <hi>Benthem</hi> &amp; <hi>Scouwenburgh,</hi> taking, pilling and ranſacking of churches and moneſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, robbing all the country people, with an vnruled crue of Souldiers, ſurpriſing, afflicting and murdering them with ſuch horrible cruelty, that it is vnpoſſible to expreſſe it, &amp; all vnder the coulour of the ſeruice of God &amp; the king.</p>
                  <p>The Proteſtant princes aſſembled againe in Ianuary at <hi>Collen,</hi> for they are ſo tormented y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many of them are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to abandon their houſes, wel perceiuing what they ought to feare. Thoſe of <hi>Oſnaburgh</hi> denied the Spaniards the demaunded ranſome of the Citty, oppoſing and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelues with their Lord and Biſhop (who is of the houſe of <hi>Bruynſwicke</hi>) againſt the Spaniards.</p>
                  <p>The like is done by thoſe of the citty of <hi>Munſter</hi> and take in ſouldiers to their ayde, ſo that the enterpriſe which the Spaniards had vndertaken (by the winking or eye ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Prince Elector of <hi>Collen</hi>), is failed them. It is manifeſt that they procured to make the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> great, and that they would ſée that all the Netherlandes,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16254:11"/>
                     <hi>Cleue</hi> and <hi>Gulich</hi> with their neighbors, might fall vnder the ſame, rather then that they ſhould be inherited by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants or their lawfull Princes. Heereupon the Princes had appointed to méete at <hi>Auſborch</hi> in December laſt.</p>
                  <p>The citties in the Dukedome of <hi>Cleue</hi> were perſwaded, that the Spaniardes would not any more vndertake any ſéedges or to ſurpriſe any thing more by violence: wherfore thoſe of <hi>Calcar, Goch, Cleue</hi> &amp; others, reſolued, to reſiſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and to ſtand by, and aſiſt one another, to defend themſelues with their weapons, and not to let in their enemy: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that thoſe of <hi>Calcar</hi> are great Catholiques, and their Cittizens greatly enclined to the olde Religion. They were moſte fearefully aſſaulted by this Catholique Spaniſh campe. For when the cittizens had begun moſte valiantly to reſiſt and defend themſelues, and beate downe their enemies: there was no remedy nor fauour found, but were after the moſt rigorous ſorte ſo aſſaulted, and enemy-like battered, their gates throwen downe, and after many liues loſt, the Citty was taken vpon the Chriſtmas euen laſt, which brought ſuch terrible aſtoniſhment to the other citties, that the people fled in great heapes, and were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the colde winter to leaue the country. By reaſon whereof thoſe of <hi>Goch</hi> ſent Embaſſadors to the Admirant at <hi>Rees,</hi> to make an agréement with him, as alſo did the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther citties: but it was in vaine, he ſends his men thether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and deceiptfully entred <hi>Wees,</hi> (lying an houres go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>Goch</hi>) which they enſconced ſtrongly and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned the cittie of <hi>Goch</hi> to take in 500. footemen and thrée companies of horſe of his: Many cittizens flying were defended by the horſemen of <hi>Nimmeghen,</hi> inſomuch that the enemy durſt not touch them vpon the Plaine betwéene <hi>Goch</hi> and <hi>Cleue.</hi> The ſouldiers were ſuffered to enter, but as the horſemen being come before the citty, the entraunce was by the Cittizens (in ſhutting their gates) hindred, wherat the chieftaine of the ſaid horſe threatned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: meane while the cittizens got ſauegard from the Prince &amp; Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16254:12"/>
which is the cauſe that in February there returnd ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Goch</hi> thetherwards again. What wil follow, time &amp; experience will teach: But it ſéemes that the Admirant, knowing well enough how he ſtandeth with the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> will not paſſe much for ſauegards, but will proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his intent.</p>
                  <p>For concluſion we will (for this time) commit the cauſe to God, beſéeching him to preſerue &amp; defend al louers of the patrimony, from al ſuch imoderate, cruelty of the Spaniſh tyrants, which are neuer glutted with ſpilling of guiltleſſe bloud, and more then brutall rauiſhing of yong Virgins, and chaſt matrons, and vnmeaſurable murtherous robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Their obſtinacy, which they vſe to their frée Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries is ſo great, that it cannot be thought nor expreſſed in more odious ſort, but they will ſurpaſſe all in wickedneſſe, not reſpecting any of what religion ſoeuer, young or olde. This (louing and kinde Reader) is a faire glaſſe for vs, wherein we may ſpeculate and ouercaſt what wee ſhould he to expect of theſe notable gallants, if they ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe vs. Therefore let euery one, watch and pray to the omnipotent God, for mercy and aſſiſtaunce, that hee will giue vs all a valient vnited heart, whereby wee may preuent all theſe ſaid cruel tyranies of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard. To his honour and glory, and the good and ſaluation of vs all. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:16254:12"/>
                  <head>The Whale of Berckhey. Or A deſcription of the great Fish which ſtranded <hi>or came on shore at</hi> Berckhey <hi>in Holland, the</hi> third of Februarie 1598. With a breefe relation of ſuch things as happened therevpon and ſince the ſame.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <head>I</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is moſt certaine and true,<note place="margin">
                           <p>I will for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uities ſake, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit al ſignes &amp; tokens which haue happened in the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or the ayre, at diuers times, and will onely tell ſome hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of ſome Sea-monſters, being that the ſubiect of our writing, is of a Sea-monſter. In the time of the Romiſh Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> the 4. (as <hi>Bapt. Fulg</hi> writeth) there was taken on the ſhore, a Sea-knight, whoſe ſhape was much like a man, excepting that on his head he had two ſmall hornes, and but two fingers on each hand, his feete like tailes, and at his armes he had two little wings, like vnto thoſe of a Bat. Heerevpon preſently enſued the bloody warres which the <hi>Dolphin</hi> of Fraunce, ſonne to <hi>Charles</hi> the 7. made againſt the <hi>Switzers</hi> by the inſtigation of the ſaid Pope <hi>Eugenius,</hi> who would (againſt the Emperour <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> his will) haue had the ſynod which was appointed at <hi>Baſel,</hi> to be helde in <hi>Italy.</hi> Alſo the ſaid Pope was the cauſe that <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> the young King of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> broke the truce which was made with <hi>Amurath</hi> the Turkiſh Emperour, in diſcharging him by his Papall power, of the deere and great oathe wherwith the ſaid peace was confirmed and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, wherewith <hi>Amurath</hi> being mooued and ſpited, aſſembled a mightie hoaſt of horſe, men and footemen, to reuenge himſelfe vppon <hi>Ladiſlaus.</hi> It chaunced that both armies ioyning together, the Turkes began to faint, which <hi>Amurathe</hi> perceiuing, lifting vp his eyes and hands to heauen, ſaid: See Ieſus Chriſt, this is the truce which thy Chriſtians (in ſwearing by thy name) haue made me. If now thou beeſt a rightfull God, defend thine and mine honor. Theſe wordes were no ſooner ſpoken by <hi>Amurath,</hi> but the <hi>Hungarians</hi> and the <hi>Polonians</hi> were put to flight, and the moſt of them ſlaine: amongſt the reſt the King <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> and <hi>Iulianus Ceſarinus,</hi> the Popes Embaſſadour. This happened neere vnto <hi>Varna,</hi> Anno. 1444. the 10. of Nouember, according to the writing of <hi>Bonfino lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 3. Shortly after this, <hi>Eugenius</hi> was depoſed, and a Duke of Sauoye ſet in his place. You that ſay that one is not bound to keepe any oathe or faith vnto Heretickes, chawe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chawe this accident. An other example. In Anno. 1281. it happened that ſome Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men caught in their net a Sea-monſter, much like a Lyon, which as ſoone as it was aboue water, began to moane and lament, as a man that is greeued, and was brought aliue to <hi>Rome</hi> to the Pope <hi>Martin</hi> the 4. Shortly after enſued the Sicilian Veſpers, which is the time when (in the Papiſtrie) are ſung the Veſpers, there being through the intiſement of Pope <hi>Nicolas</hi> the third, and through the complot of the king of <hi>Arragon</hi> (on the Eaſter daye) murdered all the Frenche garriſons, which the French king had in Sicilia.</p>
                           <p>In the yeere of our Lord 1522. there was ſeene at the ſea ſide neere Rome, a Sea-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, hauing the face of a woman with great breſts, her haire all intangled, with long eares like a Beagle, but in ſhape more like an Ape then a man. At that time <hi>Sultan Soliman,</hi> ſunne to the Turkiſh Emperor <hi>Zelim,</hi> beſiedged the Knights of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> which kept <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and ſo ſtrongly aſſaulted them, that he made himſelfe maiſter of the whole Iland.</p>
                           <p>A little before that, <hi>Poſthumes Albinus</hi> the Romaine Generall, with his whole armie, was by the French diſcomfited: It ſeemed in many places, that the Sea was on fire, which was a ſigne of the enſuing burning warre, which at that time was kindled in many places of the worlde.</p>
                        </note> that God hath often declared through tokens and ſignes in the ayre, the earth, and from the deapth of the ſeas, that his mightie hand was raiſed, to puniſh lands and nations, for their wickedneſſe, by warre, peſtilence or famine: peruſe the holye Scriptures, reade the olde Chronicles, and that which I tell you héere will be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt vnto you: and yet although euery man can eſpie a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, yet can none deuine what they ſignifie. It hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God Almightie to hide that from vs, thereby to kéepe vs more in awe and feare.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:16254:13"/>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <p>For when that in the yéere 1598, the Sea had vomited a mightie Whale on our ſhore at <hi>Berckhey,</hi> who in euery ones ſight was horrible to beholde, I alſo was amazed and admired ſo rare a thing, and (as all the reſt) doubted that ſome ſtrange matter would enſue thervpon, and that God was diſpleaſed: but no one could imagine what would follow, nor what God had ordained thereby. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that out of <hi>Brabant</hi> there came tumbling a pamphlet, wherein at large the full ſignification thereof was diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, no otherwiſe but if God had tolde the writer what he had diſpoſed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="section">
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <p>I helde my peace, my mouth and my pen, hoping that God ere long, would ſhew that he had not cauſed that Whale to ſtrande in <hi>Holland,</hi> as a token that he ment to reduce theſe Netherlands vnder the yoake of that cruell monſter, who ſéeketh nothing elſe but through fire and ſworde, to deſtroye theſe excellent countries, he is like a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16254:13"/>
Whale, who whatſoeuer he catcheth in his chops, he ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, teareth, and deuoureth without mercie, for I haue hoped alwayes that God would make the Spaniſh tyrant ſtarue for hunger, like the Whale did after two dayes and thrée nights.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="section">
                     <head>IIII.</head>
                     <p>This Monſter was 24. elles in length, 22. téeth he had, which all like hornes long and ſharpe fitted the one within the other in the hollow vault of his mouthe, his eyes ſmal, ſtanding déepe within his head,<note n="*" place="margin">Membrum virile.</note> the thing was great and long, two finnes he had, each of two elles long, &amp; broade ¾ and ½, he had a toung of huge bigneſſe, in his throate lay a monſterous bladder like an Oxe gut, which vomitted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of filthe, which with great ſtreames flowed from his body, in ſo much that what through his ſtincke, and what through his bigneſſe, he was moſt horrible in euery ones ſight.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="section">
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <p>This all fits right well with Signor the Admirant, who (<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <p>Conueniunt rebus nomina ſepe ſuis.</p>
                           <p>The Generall of the male-co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiſh campe, is, <hi>Franciſcus Mendoſus Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirandus Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragonie Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chio Quadelles Valdepenas</hi> &amp;c <hi>Mendoſus, a, um,</hi> is as much as a man that is full of lyes or faults: <hi>Admirandus,</hi> a wonderfull and notable fellow: <hi>Valdepenas,</hi> is as much as one who greatlye plagueth and moleſteth other men, and ſhall in the ende, greatly be puniſhed for the ſame. And that theſe names agree with his conditions, he ſhewed as ſoone as he was paſſed the <hi>Rhine,</hi> for hauing taken the cittie of <hi>Orſay,</hi> and the Caſtell yet holding out, he went himſelfe in perſon accompanied with a hangman, and a Fryer, to the caſtell, threatning them, that if they were not reſolued to render vp the Forte, they might prepare themſelues to be confeſſed, and that the hange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was there ready to hang them: nay more, himſelfe tooke the halters out of the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans hands, and lifting them on high, ſhewed them vnto the beſieged. I beleeue not, that on our ſide, there be any captaine or commaunder, that would haue helped the hangman ſo well in his office. "That which ſome eſteeme for a great miſerie and calamitie, (<hi>viz.</hi> to leeſe houſe and lands) thoſe of <hi>Cleue</hi> &amp; <hi>Munſter,</hi> eſteeme it a great happineſſe, and are very glad, that in abandoning all, they may eſcape bare and naked out of the tyrants hands.</p>
                        </note> as his name ſignifies) is parlous gallant, with 24000. men he paſſed the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and firſt tooke <hi>Orſay.</hi> Euery one was affrighted through out all the land, each cittie imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that they leueld at them, yea ſéemed that at a clappe he would haue taken all the Citties which lye héere belowe on the banke. But it was not ſo, the caſe goes otherwiſe, he whetteth his téeth in the lands of <hi>Cleue</hi> &amp; <hi>Munſter,</hi> "where he ſo abuſeth both men and women, that no body can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure by him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="section">
                     <pb facs="tcp:16254:14"/>
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <p>By the ſmall eyes of the Whale, is ſignified the little foreſight and vnaduiſedneſſe of the Admirant, who was ſo gréedy to conuay his great hoaſt déeper into the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, that he tooke no care for his foode,<note n="(a)" place="margin">All wiſe Generals, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt, where and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence the campe may be beſt victuailed: but this won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull fellowe comming ouer the <hi>Rhine</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Corne was ripe, would not giue the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen of <hi>Zut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> any ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, whereby in lying peaceably in the countrie, they might haue victualed the Campe. But willingly gaue them reſpite and leaſure, to flie into the ſtrong Citties: inſomuch, that ſhortly after, his Souldiours through hunger were conſtrained to eate Coletwort-ſtalkes, and clodded blood of beaſts: rootes, and hearbes, &amp;c. And whileſt that the land was full of food and victuals, they ſaid, it is not royall, nor honourable inough, for the King to take contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his ſubiects: but now when the clownes were fled, he graunteth them ſauegarde.</note> for the Countrie people fled, and conuayed the Corne and cattle away, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that Signor, through famine was conſtrained to eat Colewort ſtalkes, for they could not get any bread: yet when this hungrie crew, came into the<note n="(b)" place="margin">So I call the citties of <hi>Cleue</hi> and <hi>Munſter:</hi> but truly the Spaniards doth not now eſteeme or holde them for Neutrall, but as his owne, and reſpecteth them no more then hee dooth <hi>Deutecum,</hi> which alwayes heeretofore hath beene on our ſide. And euen as the Pope did giue this king of Spaines predeceſſors, the land of <hi>America,</hi> (whereof the Heathen king <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibalyba</hi> greatly wondered ſaying: Surely this Pope muſt needs be ſome great foole, to giue my countrie and citties, wherein he hath not a foote of right, to an other.) Euen as great right and reaſon hath he to giue <hi>Albertus</hi> (who is one of his beſt ſonnes) the Lordſhips of <hi>Cleue</hi> and <hi>Munſter,</hi> if ſo it may pleaſe his holineſſe: But to whom ſoeuer the ſaid Prouinces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth of <hi>Cleue</hi> and <hi>Munſter,</hi> the Spaniards ſuppoſeth to haue good right in them, ſaying that at the time when <hi>Knipperdolincke</hi> and <hi>Iohn Becolt</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> with the Annabaptiſts in Anno. 1533. had made themſelues maiſter of the Cittie of <hi>Munſter,</hi> the Biſhop beeing not able ynough to take the Cittie againe, and to beate out the Annabaptiſts, he beſought thoſe of the houſe of <hi>Burgundie</hi> for ayde, promiſing that himſelfe and his ſubiects at any time thereafter, ſhould bee thankfull vnto them for it. Now is it the right time (ſaide the Spaniards) to accompliſh that promiſe, and therefore they thinke they may lawfully call in their debts and to pay themſelues. See how eaſily a ſtaffe is found when one will beate the dogge, if one cannot finde a ſtraight one, a crooked one will ſerue the turne.</note> Neutrall citties and there lodged in<note n="c" place="margin">Some poore Cittizens, which with their hands and the ſweate of their browes get their liuing, are peſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with ten, fifteene, yea twentie ſouldiers in their houſen, other ſome 25. 30. 36. more or leſſe, which eate and conſume all what the miſerable Inhabitants of the neutrall citties, are able any way to get. My Lords they ſit at the table making good cheere. The hoaſt like a Page muſt ſtand behind them, bare headed to ſerue them, yea he muſt ſee them with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, before they will vouchſafe to touch one bit of the good meate which is ſet before them. Where Signior the Spaniard hath any gouernment, there the Gentlemen and Cittizens of the Citties muſt ſtand with cap in hand, and bow themſelues to a filthie rotten, pockie, Spaniſh baſketmaker, and ſuch a one muſt bee called Signior, as is woorſe then the moſt baſeſt Boore in all the <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
                        </note> heaps, liſten what they did: Browne bread, and powdred fleſh they ſcorned to eate, throwing it at their hoaſts féete,<note n="d" place="margin">Yea ſo wicked and immodeſt are theſe pockie abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable wretches, and heathniſh Chriſtians, that they will not reſpect wenches of eight, nine, tenne, eleuen, or twelue yeares of age.</note> and through their villanies they haue vndone many a maide and honeſt woman.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="section">
                     <pb facs="tcp:16254:14"/>
                     <head>VII</head>
                     <p>Through the vnneceſſarie and vgly tongue of the whale is ſignified,<note place="margin">Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſhips the laſt yeare were come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pepper countrie, and that the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then King at <hi>Bantam</hi> for a ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney had gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke in his countrie, hee notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſoone broke his promiſe, ſeeking to deſtroy our men, contrarie to his oath and promiſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being reprooued, and demaunded the cauſe thereof, he anſwered that hee had no bone in his tongue, and that he could turne and winde the ſame at his will and pleaſure, this may likewiſe be applied to the Spaniard, for he breaketh his oath and promiſe as often &amp; when he liſteth. And being he cannot condemne thoſe of <hi>Cleue</hi> and <hi>Munſter</hi> of hereſie, and that the olde rule of the Concile of <hi>Trent</hi> (faith ought not to be held vnto heretickes, can take no place there, The Admirant, when complaints are made that hee hath not helde his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, anſwereth. The ſeruice of god and the king require ſo much, that I cannot keepe my promiſe. Hath he not cauſe and reaſon ynough, thinke you, to breake and violate the oath. It is euen with the Spaniards as it was whilome with the ambitious heathens, <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> and others, which were wont to ſay: <hi>Si violandum eſt Ius, regnandi cauſa violandum eſt. Alpen, Anholt,</hi> and <hi>Meurs,</hi> vnto which the Cardinall vnder his hand and Scale had graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted neutralitie, haue notwithſtanding by the Admirant bene taken.</note> that the promiſes which the Spaniarde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs, are vaine and of no woorth. It is ſtinke, it is filth, burning and murthering which ſtickes in his heart, and herewith his minde is ſtuffed &amp; puffed vp like the bellie of the whale, with filthie infection.<note n="f" place="margin">The Spaniard ſeemes to haue minde vpon nothing ſo much, as vpon the Romiſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the furtherance thereof. In ſo much that his Catholicque Maieſtie, the king of Spaine is eſteemed to be the trueſt and faithfulleſt ſeruant vnto the Romiſh ſeate. Vnder this hypocriticall vaile, they ſeeke to cloake their inſatiable ambition, couetouſneſſe, and bloodthirſt. Euery where that they lie in <hi>Cleueland,</hi> they do no more fauour the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licques, then thoſe of the reformed religion or others, yea the places could be named where they haue broken the Churches and monuments which by our people were leaft vndefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</note> Shew of holineſſe and pariurie are the two ſinnes, wherewith hee purpoſeth to ſubdue the <hi>Netherlands.</hi> He hath heretofore done many an exployt, but ſince that his deceit came to light a very litle. Al his deuices are deceit, enormious in each ones ſight, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one feares his crueltie, be they proteſtants<note n="g" place="margin">I ſpeake of ſome ſuch Papiſts, which hauing taſted the Barbarous cruelties of the Spaniards, know full well that they fauour none, but euen ſuch ouer which they haue no power. Thoſe which long and wiſh for the victorie of the Spaniards wiſh for their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, be they whatſoeuer they may be,</note> or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, they know his dealings.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="section">
                     <head>VIII.</head>
                     <p>The Whale lying on the ſtrand, euery one that came thither ſhortned his taile, cutting a péece thereof. The Spaniardes taile is alſo well ſhortned, for by reaſon of the hunger which the poore Souldiers endured, many haue dyed, and many other haue beene ſlaine
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16254:15"/>
by our men, alſo many fled away, both by day and by night, inſomuch that his hoaſt is leſſened by the one halfe,<note n="*" place="margin">When the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy marched vp to <hi>Deutecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> his excellencie forſooke the place where he lay, enſconſing himſelfe vpon the dyke in battaile arraye, a long while expecting the enemie, who with his campe laye at <hi>Elterberch,</hi> about a halfe league from our campe. The enemy euery moment was at an allarum, where his excellencie neuer made any, neither was this luſtie Spaniard ſo bolde as with his great armie, once to aſſaile our little heape. This is the right ſitting vnder the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the higheſt, and to dwell vnder the ſhadowe of the almightie, <hi>Pſal</hi> 91.1. Many of iudgement &amp; vnderſtanding, eſteeme, and hope that the Lord of hoaſts hath ordained this yeare many great victories to his excellencie, as in the yeare laſt paſt.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any hurt or hinderance to ours. Oh a ſhrewd knocke for theſe blood thirſtie hounds, how vnaduiſed was he, that counſailed them to come into theſe watery landes, in the which already they haue endured ſo great ſhame.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="section">
                     <head>IX.</head>
                     <p>As héeretofore the warlicke Romaine<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <p>The renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Hanniball</hi> had at diuers times diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi> boaſts, eſpecially the victorie which he obtained by <hi>Cannas</hi> in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulia,</hi> is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, where ſo manye thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of <hi>Romaines</hi> dyed, that <hi>Hannibals</hi> ſouldiers beſides other ſpoiles, got from the hands of the ſlaine, three buſhels of Rings, and if <hi>Hanniball</hi> at that time had followed on his victorie, he might eaſily haue taken <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſubdued all the Romaine Empire. Shortlye after he came with his armie (which alwayes was woont to vanquiſh,) into Italye, at which time the Romaines made <hi>Q. Fabius</hi> a Dictator, who perceiuing the inſatiable deſire of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niball,</hi> his experience and order in the warres, enſconced himſelfe wel, and would not for any thing giue <hi>Hanniball</hi> battaile, but laye ſtill, by reaſon whereof he was of euery one eſteemed a coward, but he cared not for that, and ſo long he lay ſtill with his forces, vntill <hi>Hannibals</hi> Campe, with the long lying had conſumed it ſelfe, and came to ſhame, wherof the Romains gaue him this praiſe.</p>
                           <q>Vnus homo nobis canctando reſtituit rem.</q>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Fabius</hi> in ſitting ſtill, vanquiſhed the valiant venturous <hi>Hanniball.</hi> So hath alſo our Lorde the noble <hi>Count Maurice</hi> ſhewed his great experience in the martiall affaires, in driuing the enemie with all his mightie troupes out of the land, without blow or ſhocke. O noble blood of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> O prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> mighteſt thou once caſt downe thy eyes and bebolde how Iacke of Spaine is bearded by<note n="“" place="margin">Good reaſon had Earle <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Manſuelt,</hi> to ſay (when he heard that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (of laudable memorie) had a ſonne borne, whoſe name was <hi>Mauritius,</hi>) If this childe haue his Fathers wiſdome, and the vallour of his Graund-father <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Prince of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> he will giue the King of Spaine enough to doe.</note> 
                        <hi>Maurice</hi> thy ſonne, migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thou once ſée how hee hath clipped and ſhortned his taile, thy heart would reioyce, and thy ioyes be redoubled, in beholding thy ſonnes vallour and vertues.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="section">
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:16254:15"/>
                     <head>X.</head>
                     <p>Next to<note n="a" place="margin">Earle <hi>Adolph</hi> of <hi>Naſſau</hi> was made Emperor in Anno 1292. and raigned 6. yeares, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining greate warres againſt <hi>Albertus</hi> duke of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Adolph</hi> of <hi>Naſſau</hi> came to the Empire <hi>Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> a Prince of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria. Adolph</hi> ſuffered each one to kéepe and hold his goods and lands, each their Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and their people in peace.<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <p>And beeing that the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie whereof we haue here ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, is worthie of memorie, for the reſemblance of the matters which happen now, and being that it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue three hundreth yeares ago that they happened, and therefore not ſo well knowne, I wil for the delight of the wel-willing Reader, rehearſe the ſumme thereof, as it is written by <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias Smilers, lib</hi> 1. <hi>de Repub. Heluet.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Albertus</hi> was a great enemie and an enuior of the freedome of the Switzers, he had many children. All which hee intending to inrich, ſought to ſtretch out his commaundement farre and nigh about his Empire, and hath rent and torne diuers Lordſhips from the ſame, and ioyned them to his houſe, as his owne: hee was very troubleſome and dammageable vnto all his bordering neighbours, he feared not, nor was not aſhamed, (with diſhonourable and lawleſſe reaſons) yea with open might to demande and make his owne, that which belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vnto others. The ſpirituall perſons which were rich and wealthie, hee endeuoured to bring the matter to ſuch a paſſe, that they ſhould ſell him their rights, or that they would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him and his children for euer, for their hereditarie Defendors, Lords, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors. Alſo he beſought the Earles and Barrons of <hi>Switzerland</hi> to acknowledge the Lords of <hi>Auſtria</hi> for their Land-Lords, which before were ſubiect to none but to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Emprour.</p>
                           <p>Hee alſo forcibly detained the paternall inheritance of his brothers ſonne, ouer whom hee was appoynted Tutor. Some citties did <hi>Albertus</hi> (what through prayers, faire promiſes and threats) teare and ſeparate from the Empire, and clouted them to the houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> But the moſt part haue denied his importunate requeſts, and would not in any wiſe ſubmit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to him. Shortly after that the Embaſſadors were returned, many of the Citties and Lordſhips of the Switzers ſent vnto him certaine perſons, beſeeching his Emperiall Maieſtie that it might pleaſe him, to confirme them the rights and preuiledges which his predeceſſors had graunted them. Wherevpon in great rage he anſwered, that hee would doo that which they requeſted, euen as they had granted him his demaundes: and further, that hee had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained certaine Gouernours which he would ſend them, and by them they ſhould vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his will more at large. And for Gouernours, hee appoynted one named <hi>Griſlerus,</hi> and another named <hi>Peregrinus Landenbergius.</hi> Theſe Gouernours of the Emperours at the firſt dealed very kindly and diſcreetly with the people, thereby ſeeking to ſteale the hearts of the communaltie, &amp; to make them obedient to <hi>Albertus.</hi> But ſeeing that they profited nothing that way, they aſſayed what crueltie and tyrannie would worke. For breuities ſake, wee will paſſe ouer many things wherewith <hi>Albertus</hi> Gouernours tried the good Switzers, and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie tell what <hi>Griſlerus</hi> hath done, who was Gouernour of <hi>Switz</hi> and <hi>Vri.</hi> He builded a ſtrong Caſtle by his Lords command neare <hi>Altorf,</hi> which in their tongue he named <hi>Twing Vri,</hi> &amp;c. Which is as much as the yoake by which thoſe of <hi>Vri</hi> ſhall be brought to the vttermoſt ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie and obedience. This Caſtle being finiſhed, he cauſed within <hi>Altorff</hi> to be ſet vp a high Pole, and vpon the top, a flat Cap, commaunding that euery man with vncouering of the head and bowing of the knee, ſhould honour the ſaid Cap, as much as if the Emperour or himſelfe in perſon were preſent, knowing well that thoſe which hated the Emperor &amp; him, would neuer doe the ſame, but he did it to the end that he might haue occaſion to attache thoſe which were ſuſpected. It chaunced that one <hi>William Tell,</hi> at ſundrie times paſſing by the Cap, honoured not the ſame, which being reported to the Gouernour, he ſought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe himſelfe, in ſaying, that he knew not that the matter was of ſuch importance. But <hi>Griſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> not content heerewith, tooke one of <hi>William Tels</hi> ſonnes (whom he knew the Father loued beſt, and laying an Appell vpon the childes head, ſaid, vnleſſe then you ſhoote of this Appell without hurting the childe, thou ſhalt dye. The Father anſwered that hee would rather dye then aduenture it. Well (quoth the Gouernour,) except that thou dooſt it, both thy ſelfe and thy ſonne ſhall dye. <hi>William Tel</hi> perceiuing, that prayers would take no place there, tooke the Bowe into his hand, and there through Gods helpe, ſhot off the Apell without touching the childe. The Gouernour had marked that <hi>William Tel</hi> had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken two arrowes out of the Quiuer, whereof the one he had ſtucke at his girdell, wherfore he asked what he ment thereby. <hi>William Tel</hi> anſwered, that he ment nothing thereby but that it was the order of Archers. The Gouernour not content therewith, would needs know the grounde of the matter, promiſing him, that if hee would tell him the trueth, his life ſhould not be touched. <hi>William Tell</hi> vpon theſe promiſes, ſaid: that his intent was (if he had ſlaine his ſonne with the one arrow) to haue killed the Gouernour with the other. O wicked wretch (quoth <hi>Griſlerus</hi>) thy life will I not take, but I will commit thee to a priſon, where thou ſhalt ſee neither ſunne nor moone, nor ſpeake to any body, and there thou ſhalt end thy daies. And cauſing his hands and feete to be bound, tooke him with him in a ſhip going from <hi>Vri</hi> to <hi>Cuſnac.</hi> When being in the middeſt of the lake, there aroſe ſuch a mightie ſtorme, that they eſteemed themſelues loſt, the Marriners not being able to guide the Ship, abandoned the ſame, to the mercie of the windes and the waters, and <hi>Griſlerus</hi> in this diſtreſſe, asked if there were no meanes to get a ſhore, whatſoeuer it might coſt. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon one of his ſeruants replyed, that he doubted not but they ſhould get a ſhore, if <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Tell</hi> might ſtand at the Helme, for he was a ſtrong man, and very expert at Sea, which they hearing, vnbound <hi>William Tell,</hi> and ſet him at the Helme, where he laboured greatly to bring the Ship neere the land, which within a while did: and eſpying a great Rocke (which at this day is yet called <hi>Tels</hi> Rocke) he ſteered the Barke fully thereupon, and at the approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, leauing the Helme, and catching his bowe and arrowes, leapt ouer boorde vppon the Rocke, and withall his might launching the Barke againe, ranne into the countrie, and the Barke after long toſſing, ſome dayes after got to <hi>Brunnen,</hi> from whence <hi>Griſlerus</hi> trauailed towards <hi>Cuſnac</hi> by land. <hi>William Tell</hi> beeing well acquainted with the wayes, hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe behinde certaine buſhes in a Valley, through the which hee knewe <hi>Griſlerus</hi> ſhould paſſe: and hauing his Bowe in a readineſſe, at the tyrants paſſing by ſhot him thorough, which done (becauſe that he would not be taken) he fled to ſome cheefe perſons which hee knew to be great enemies of the Emperours and Gouernours, vnto which he declared the matter, and hauing conſulted vppon it, tooke heart, and by little and little, droue all <hi>Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> officers out of the lande, thereby recouering their loſt freedome, which vntill this daye they holde. Compare our <hi>Albertus</hi> with his Cardinals flatte Cap, to this <hi>Albertus</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue ſpoken, and you ſhall finde, that two Egges laide by one Henne cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble one another better. <hi>Beholde the ende.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </note> Aſſoone as <hi>Albertus</hi> got the Scepter in his hande, hee made ſtrife and debate in <hi>Switzerland.</hi> The which with ſubtiltie, and afterwardes with ſtrife and odio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s practiſes he ſought to ioyne to his houſe. But <hi>Albertus</hi> aymed amiſſe, the valiant ſturdie Switzers haue (for their countries fréedome) ſpared ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goods nor blood, they ioyned togither and played the men, vntill ſuch time as they had baniſhed <hi>Albert</hi> out of the land.</p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:16254:16"/>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="section">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:16254:16"/>
                     <head>XI.</head>
                     <p>The noble bloud of the houſe of <hi>Naſſau,</hi>
                        <note n="a" place="margin">His excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie hauing dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the enemy out of <hi>Emricke</hi> rendered the ſame willinglye into the hands of the Duke of <hi>Cleue,</hi> without any wayes tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching any one in life or goods.</note> holdeth yet the ſame ſteps which <hi>Adolph</hi> long agoe ſhewed them. <hi>Albert</hi> likewiſe followeth the paces of his Graund-fathers, who tyrannized Switzerland: he ſéeketh to teare and ſeperate the land of <hi>Cleue</hi> from the Empire, as euery one may ſee.<note n="b" place="margin">Theſe bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuckers were not contented, in hauing taken the good Earle of <hi>Brookes</hi> Caſtell, and impriſoned him, but haue againſt their promiſes moſt wickedly murthered him, and burnt his body to Aſhes. Oh cruell tyrants: but O worthie Earle, who in dying in the right beleefe, didſt witneſſe the true religion with thy blood. The goods of this good Lord were publikely with the ſounde of Drum and Trumpet, ſolde in the campe, euen as the ſouldiours are vſed to fell the bootie and pillage, got of their open enemies.</note> When the Earle of <hi>Valkenſteine</hi> and <hi>Brooke,</hi> &amp;c. would haue defended his countrie, he was impriſoned, murdered, and burnt to Aſhes. You Princes of the Empire, how long will you ſuffer this, how long will you ſléepe with open eyes, is it not yet enough, the Spaniarde himſelfe ſaith, that you are Lyons<note n="c" place="margin">That ſome thinke that <hi>Albertus</hi> with his ayders, vpon the writings and requeſts of any King or Prince, would leaue and abandon the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate citties, is in vaine; But will do as of late yeares did the Earle <hi>Tunis</hi> of <hi>Oldenborch,</hi> who hauing forcibly taken the houſe or caſtell of <hi>Dolmerhorſt</hi> with the appurtenances. Thoſe of <hi>Spier,</hi> in the Emperours name, wrote vnto him, that he ſhould render the ſame againe to thoſe vnto whom it did lawfully belong. The Earle hauing receiued the Letters (after the contents read) helde them a prittie while to his eare, ſaying. I heare no Gunnes, as if he would haue ſaide, what I haue purchaſed by force of armes, I will not ſuffer to bee taken awaye againe by papers.</note> but bite not.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="section">
                     <head>XII.</head>
                     <p>O thou God of hoaſts, vouchſafe mercifully to beholde thy countrie, and defend the ſame with thy ſtrong arme, againſt theſe halfe white Moores: Suffer them not O Lord, to execute the rancour of their hearts, againſt the people which thou haſt choſen for thy heritage. It is true that we deſerue to be wholie caſt from the ſight of thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred face. We haue deſerued to be robbed of thy holye worde, which now thou teacheſt vs: yet Lorde for thy names ſake, fauour vs yet and alwayes, ſhew thy mercie to thy Church.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="section">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:16254:17"/>
                     <head>XIII.</head>
                     <p>O you ſtates of the vnited lands, who haue choſen for your Lieutenant the <hi>Counte Maurice,</hi> melt all your ſpirits together, beſéech GOD continually to encreaſe in you (through his goodneſſe) the ſpirit of<note n="(a)" place="margin">Concordia res parue creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt.</note> concorde<note n="(b)" place="margin">It is an olde ſaying: <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſedendo vincit.</hi>
                        </note> wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and<note n="(c)" place="margin">Woe to the lande whoſe king is a child, eyther in years or vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> vnderſtanding to the building of his church, and the countries good. But firſt ſéeke for Gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, further (by all meanes) his Church, then will hee caſt his bleſſing vpon this land, and aboliſh all <hi>Achitophels</hi> complots: and at your ſoules departure from hence, receiue them vp to him in his celeſtiall dwelling.</p>
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Religio verè ligat,</hi> Where the hearts of men are not through the bonde of true religion bound together, there is no foundation. Therefore, all thoſe which ſeeke the countries wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, muſt alſo and eſpecially procure the furtherance of the true Catholicke reformed religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in euery place where it is poſſible, ſetting wiſe and learned men to preache the ſame, and ordaining good Schooles, wherein youth may bee well educated and taught, not onely in ſpeach and ſciences, but eſpecially in the true religion, to which ende the Emperiall goods ought to be vſed, which doone, there ſhall be no occaſion giuen to the enimies of the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the patrimonie, to ſay, that we driue away the Monckes and Fryers, not ſo much through zeale of religion, as becauſe we might get the fingering of the ſpirituall goods.</note>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16254:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> LETTER OF THE EMPEROVR OF GER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie, to the Admirant of <hi>Arragon,</hi> Generall for the Archeduke <hi>Albertus,</hi> in the Counties of <hi>Cleue</hi> and <hi>Munſter,</hi> &amp;c. With the Admirants anſwere.</p>
                  <p>The conſpiracie of the three Bishops.</p>
                  <p>The death of the Earle of Brooke.</p>
                  <p>The Admirants Letter to the counſaile of <hi>Gulich.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The liſt of the Souldiours leuied by the proteſtant Princes of <hi>Germanie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Faithfully tranſlated out of the Dutch copie Printed at</hi> Roterdam.</p>
                  <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Iohn VVolfe,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in Popes head Alley, neere vnto the Exchange. 1599.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16254:18"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16254:18"/>
                  <head>A Letter of the Emperour <hi>Roduphus the ſecond, to</hi> Don Franciſco de men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dozza, <hi>Admirant of</hi> Arragon, <hi>Generall of the army</hi> of the King of Spaine, in the Lands of <hi>Gulich</hi> and <hi>Cleue,</hi> touching the dammages by him done in the Empire.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Rodulphus</hi> by the grace of God the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, choſen Romaine Emperour, at all times an augmenter of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, in <hi>Germany, Hungaria, Bohemia, Dalmatia, Croatia</hi> and <hi>Sclauonia</hi> &amp;c. king, Archduke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy, Steyr, Keredten, Gray</hi> and <hi>Wittenberch,</hi> Earle of <hi>Tiroll</hi> &amp;c. ſend gréeting to the well-borne, our eſpeciall beloued <hi>Don Franciſco de mendoſſa,</hi> Admirant of the kingdome of <hi>Arragon,</hi> Marqueſſe of <hi>Quadelles,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Calatranonian</hi> order, Commaunder at <hi>Valazenas,</hi> Generall vnder our beloued bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Albertus</hi> Archduke of <hi>Auſtria:</hi> alſo to <hi>V. N.</hi> and <hi>N.</hi> to all and euery Regiment, Admiranty, Coronels, Captaines Lieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants and Commaunders of Souldiers horſe and foote, of what nation, State and condition ſoeuer vnto which theſe our credible letters may appeare, be ſhewed or declared, to ſuch as remaine in our Empire, or the Fortreſſes, ground, bottom, Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Townes, Sconces, and Riuers of the ſame, by Water or Land, wee make knowne, that our Princes and Lordes of the Netherlandiſh and Weſtphalian <hi>Croytes</hi> eſpecially the high-borne <hi>Iohn Wilhem,</hi> Duke of <hi>Gulich, Cleue,</hi> and <hi>Berge</hi> &amp;c. our beloued Nephew, who of a longtime moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediently had made knowne and highly complained vnto vs in what manner you Admirant, with a great Hoaſt, Force and Might, yea aboue 30000. armed men, are departed out of <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant</hi> in the ende of the moneth of September laſt paſt, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently taken your way through the Dukedome of <hi>Gulich,</hi> in the ſame month forcing, and beſetting his Citty of <hi>Orſoy,</hi> and after that, you haue ſent certaine thouſands of horſe and foote o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the <hi>Rhyne,</hi> where they haue caſt a Sconce, and on both ſides
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16254:19"/>
of the ſame, taken all the cattell and beaſts, great and ſmall, ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the flat land, and beſides this oppreſſed the poore people with impriſoning, ranſoming, burning, and murthering in ſuch odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſorte, as the like hath not béene heard héeretofore of any: inſomuch that the greater parte of the inhabitants and ſubiects haue béene forced to abandon their houſen, lands, and all elſe, what with their great labour they haue béene able to get: héer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with not ſatiſfied, but haue ſent the ſouldiours into the countrie of <hi>Berge</hi> (being a place appertaining to the Duke of <hi>Gulich</hi> and the late <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eringen</hi> of <hi>Dau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Earle at <hi>Valkenſteyn,</hi> dwelling vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the houſe called Brooke, haue aſſailed the ſame, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that the Earle of the houſe had rendred vp the ſame vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition of liues and goods ſaued; haue murdred diuers of the ſaid ſouldiors, and the Earle himſelfe who had the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants ſauegarde, they helde ſome dayes impriſoned and vpon a time (by the will and conſent of the Captaine who laye in the houſe) being gone to walke abroade, they haue muſt wickedlye murthered him. Meane while, the armie hath taken and forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly marched through ſome cities of <hi>Glene,</hi> as <hi>Burich, Dinſlaegen, Holt, Rees, Emmerick,</hi> with other Forts, Gentlemens houſen &amp; Villages, appertaining to the ſaid Dukedome, the which ſome of them, they haue with their Ordinance beaten downe, deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ranſacked, forced and deuoured, amongſt which were many ſpirituall and temporall perſons, without fauouring any one, but plaging and tormenting them to the vttermoſt, ſome with impriſonment, other with ſtrangling, and ſuch like, togeather with the violating and deflouring of women, damſels &amp; maides, in more filthie or beaſtlye ſorte then euer hath béene heard, and haue moreouer ſo oppreſſed the Cittie of <hi>Weſell,</hi> that they haue béene forced to pay 150. thouſand Dollars, the one halfe ready, and the other at ſhorte time, together with 1000. meaſures of Rye, which they haue béene forced to promiſe to the Chéeftains of you the Admirants campe; ouer and aboue the houſes and Lordſhips, as <hi>Kruydenberch, Weyfflyck houen,</hi> alſo the Princely Gentlemens houſen and Forts, as <hi>Lhan, Windendal, Duſport, Noiſan, Impel, Dornich, Lack<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unſen, Woremſemmerwogen,</hi> and alſo reduced the Duke of <hi>Gulich</hi> himſelfe, with his court, to the extreameſt and the vttermoſt pouertie, with many more other places, which haue béen with force taken, ranſacked and ſpoiled, whereof we haue a great number of ſpecifications ſent vs. Alſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16254:19"/>
ſome of the armie haue vaunted to dare to ſuppreſſe and driue away the Duke in perſon. Aboue all this you Admirant with your Spaniſh ſouldiours, haue attempted to beſet ſome Citties in the Prouince of <hi>Munſter,</hi> and thoſe which denyed your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds, you haue by force compelled and taken; alſo you haue cauſed the ſaid biſhopricke, with the Epiſcopall gouernour and counſailor of the ſame, <hi>Alexander vay Vehellen</hi> as vppermoſt, to be preſented with a quarter letter, and beſides the ſame, you haue taken and ſurpriſed the Dukedome of <hi>Cleue,</hi> together with 30. Citties and Bourghes, as well of <hi>Munſter</hi> as <hi>Cleue,</hi> to the vſe of your Souldiours for your winter Campe, and alſo wholye ſpoiled the biſhoprick of <hi>Eſſen</hi> and <hi>Weerden:</hi> alſo there are dayly vſed in the ſtrengths and Lordſhips of <hi>Gelder</hi> and other borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring neighbors, ſuch robbing, and raunſoming, that no huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie nor trade of marchandiſe can be excerciſed. Wherefore we are conſtrained, as alſo are all the other princes, the which ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto haue greatly ſolicited and beſéeched vs, and ſince that you haue vndertaken and attempted ſuch an vnreaſonable enterpriſe and haue not in any wiſe béene willing, by admoniſhments and warnings to abſtaine thereof: but that you Admirant without any reſpect, haue fallen vpon the peaceable countries of the holy Romaine Empire, and thoſe which are ſworne to the ſame, with ſuch an armie, yea without any leaue or warning: we nor any of our Princes, Lords &amp; eſtates, nor any of all the other Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh gouernement, expected any ſuch enimitie of the King of Spaine, and leſſe at the hands of our moſt déerely beloued bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Albertus</hi> Archeduke, &amp;c. but to the contrarie, haue alwayes truſted vpon good and friendly neighbourhood, where now you haue ſuppreſſed the lands (ſubiects of the Empire) with your ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours, made the ſame to pillage, and wholy ſpoiled and empo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueriſhed it, notwithſtanding that we haue héeretofore at diuers times, written our minds therof vnto you, as alſo to our beloued brother <hi>Albertus.</hi> Wherby it ſéemes that you little eſtéeme and care to follow any our aforeſaid warnings &amp; admoniſhments to the leaſt point, as you ought: wherfore it behooueth vs to haue a ſharpe &amp; néerer regarde and to vſe other means for the ſame. And therefore we commaund you Admirant of <hi>Arragon,</hi> together withall your Chieftaines, Commaunders and Soldiers, aſwell in perticuler as generall, in vertue of the power of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Romaine Maieſtie, as ſubiects to vs and the holy Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, vppon paine of life, where they may be found, and to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16254:20"/>
the others, ours and the Empires high and low ſubiects, allyes vaſſalls, &amp;c. or which are ſcituated vnder vs &amp; the holy Empire, vpon paine of ours &amp; the holy Empires Curſſe &amp; exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication together with the loſſe of their Benefices, Priuiledges, Frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, dignities, loanes, landes and goodes, in what place ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer vnder vs, and the Holy Empire, or their allyes, they may lye or remaine, which ſhall tranſgreſſe the ſame, to execute them without néed of any further declaration. Earneſtly and ſtrickt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commaunding, and willing, that you and euery one of you vnto which theſe our letters, <hi>Vidimirte</hi> and credible writinges ſhall appeare, or be ſhewed, or declared, with all your ſouldiers, without any other conduct, to depart from ours and the holie Empires territories and ground, and to diſcharge the ſame, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoning all Citties, Forts, Gentlemens houſes, villages, ſtrengthes and Sconces, which you haue (as aforeſaid) taken from the Duke of <hi>Gulich,</hi> the Biſhopricke of <hi>Munſter</hi> &amp; vs, and the ſtate of the Empire, howſoeuer they be named: and that you make reſtitution of all loſſes, and pay the dammages, by you done and cauſed, and to thoſe of <hi>Weſell</hi> and others, the forced moneys, charges and ranſomes, without any rebatement: and to the end that you Admirant may ſhew and make knowne that the death of the Earle of Brooke hath beene without your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or will: you ſhall render againe vnto the Counteſſe, (wife to the ſaid late Earle) all her taken goods, moneys, Iewels and plate, or els the full worth therof, to reeſtabliſh and ſet againe in their firſt eſtate, the moleſted ſpirituall and temporall perſons, without miſuſing them any further. And to take héede, hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forwards, not to attempt any thing in the way of enmitye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the aboue named, nor any other ſubiects of ours, or of the States of the Empire in any ſort whatſoeuer. At your perils, and behaue your ſelues accordingly which wee admoniſh you very earneſtly.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Giuen at our Caſtle of <hi>Podecray</hi> 
                        <date>the 30. of the month of December. 1598.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rodulph.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>V.L. Cardino.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ad mandatum, Ceſ. Marſt.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Arnd. Hanniwalt. in Doſso.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16254:20"/>
                  <head>An extract of the anſwere of the <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, vpon the Emperours Letter, as the</hi> writing maketh mention.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat he is not to make any accompt of this nor other letters and writings, and that if the Emperours forces ſtoode on the one ſide of him, and the holy Father the Pope, on the other ſide with his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, commaunding him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to depart, that he would not for all that obey them, as hauing a Lord, who had commaunded him to doe this exploit, except that by force of Armes he were forced to reſolue other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A conſpiracie made betweene the 3. <hi>Bishoppes, viz. the Bishop of Bamberch, the Bishop of</hi> Wirtzburgh and the Biſhop of Saltzburgh, to bring the Spaniſh inquiſition into Germany, and what en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued thereupon.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the Biſhops of <hi>Bambergh</hi> and <hi>Wirtz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> (both lying in the Mayne in <hi>Frankenland</hi>) had made a great conſpiracie and complot, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to bringe and reduce the Romiſh Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire (eſpecially <hi>Germany</hi>) vnder the damnable Spaniſh inquiſition, they met together at <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenburgh,</hi> to conferre about it, but God through his mercy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered and broke their conſpiracy, by the ſudden death of the Biſhop of <hi>Bambergh,</hi> in whoſe cloſſet, and in the Chauncery at <hi>Bambergh,</hi> were found wonderfull practiſes and deuiſes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon ſome of his Counſaile were impriſoned: It was knowne that there was a day limmitted, vpon the which diuers Nobles and others, ſhould haue béen murthered, hauing the ſaid twoo Biſhops together with the Biſhop of <hi>Saltzburgh,</hi> helde great correſpondence with the Spaniſh Admirant of <hi>Arragon,</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduct
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16254:21"/>
the ſaid Spaniards into <hi>Germany,</hi> &amp; in that ſort to make a deſtruction of the Euangeliſtes: But all was by the Biſhop of <hi>Bamberghs</hi> ſudden death detected. The biſhop of <hi>Wirtzburgh</hi> being ridden on hunting, fell from his horſe, by which fall hee burſt his arme, and was be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ides to bruſes with the fall, that he lyeth on his death-bed. The Biſhop of <hi>Saltzburgh</hi> hath ſince had the halfe of his Palmes burned whereby we ſée how ſtrangely God hath puniſhed theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Biſhopps, and brought the treaſon and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, who by their diuelliſh practiſes ſéeketh t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ranize <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all the world. God, through his wonted mercy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, manifeſt &amp; anihilate their wicked enterprizes, to the praiſe and glory of hys Holy name. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="report">
                  <head>The death of <hi>Maurice Oan-Hun,</hi> Earle <hi>of</hi> Valkenſteyn <hi>and</hi> Brooke, <hi>&amp;c. most</hi> vvickedly murthered by the Spaniardes, according <hi>to the report of one Goehaert Henſgen his</hi> ſeruant, being preſent at his death.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is knowne vnto each one that vpon the 16. of October laſt, the Admirants men came before the Earle of Brookes Caſtle, the which they demaunded to be deliuered vp into their hands, and that the Earle ſhould Caſhéere his ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for he had ſome number of Cocke feathers, (certaine men of warre ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>) The Earle anſwered that he ſtood vpon his Neutrality, &amp; that they ought to leaue him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moleſted: they not caring for that, would haue him diſmiſſe his people, and to commit himſelf vnder theyr defence and protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, withall bringing thether foure péeces of Ordinaunce, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they compelled them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>der themſelues, life and goods ſaued. When now they had entred the Forte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they tooke the Counteſſe and her little children, and conueyed them away into a monaſtary. The Souldiers of <hi>Cleue</hi> and <hi>Berge</hi> (with other people fled thether) being departed, were (notwithſtanding the conditions and promiſes) purſued, ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e and robbed, The Earle himſelfe they helde priſoner, and vſed him very hardly, compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16254:21"/>
him to goe to Maſſe, with other ſuch like moleſtations. Moreouer, certaine dayes after the taking of the Caſtle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in diſputation, they murdered his Nephew, the Lord of <hi>Herdenberch,</hi> together with a Preacher.</p>
                  <p>And by reaſon that diuers mutterings are abroad of the death of this Earle, on ſundry manners, I wil héere recount the ſame according to the confeſſion of his owne Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, <hi>Gochaert Henſgen,</hi> at <hi>Duſeldorp</hi> the fourtéenth of October.</p>
                  <p>VPon Sunday the 11. of October in the euening, the Earle being at Supper, had with him a Captaine (a braue man of perſon) together with his Iuſtice, and hys Steward: hauing all ſupped together, he went out to walk in the Court, where preſently came to him two Souldiers of the Garriſon, in blew Caſſockes, aſking if it were his pleaſure to goe abroad to walke and take the ayre? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon he replyed I: the one of them ranne vp to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine but came preſently againe, and ſo went together out of the Gate: the ſaid Earles ſeruant followed them through the Garden, where the Souldiers denyed to let him haue ſomething in this hand, for the which he aſked his ſaid Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant: yet taking vp a little ſticke, he paſſed alongſt towards the Water Mill and the fiſh ponde, where ſome fiſhe lay caught.</p>
                  <p>The Earle beckoned to the one Souldier to take it vp, who ſtood ſtill, whileſt the other at vnawares ſtroke him a mighty blow on the head with a half Pike: inſomuch that he fell to the ground, crying O Ieſu: which done, the Souldier drew his ſwoord, and therewith thruſt him thorough, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at he cryed once againe O Ieſu, but ſo fayntly that he could ſcarce be vnderſtood: meane while the other ſouldier caught vp a flaile before the Mill, wherwith he ſtroke at the Earles ſeruaunt, who perceiuing it, (being néere the ditch) leaped downe into the damme, ſo that the blowe did but touch his ſhoulder, from whence with great labour (the ſouldier ſtill thruſting at him) he got to land on the other ſide, and ſo eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. There were two other ſouldiers in the Garden, which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16254:22"/>
were commaunding the Gardiner and the Fiſhermen to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſome dead bodies which were ſlaine at the taking of the Caſtel, and were appointed by the murtherers to ſtay there. This is as much as yet is come to light of the Earles death, whoſe body (as ſome ſay) was afterwards burned in a Barne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>A Letter of the Admirant of <hi>Arra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, to the counſaile of</hi> Gulich, <hi>touching</hi> the death of the Earle of <hi>Brooke:</hi> Written <hi>two dayes after the taking of the Caſtell.</hi> Tranſlated out of Latin.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble, mightie, and honourable Lordes and friends, ſome dayes paſt we haue anſwered two of your Letters, which were brought vnto vs by the noble <hi>Henrye</hi> of <hi>Boorloe,</hi> whereby you wrote that no occaſion of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, or of any harme ſhould be giuen by the Campe, in the places about the <hi>Rhine,</hi> or other landes, appertaining to the illuſtrious Duke of <hi>Gulich,</hi> and that you alſo through your wiſdomes and experience, through méere goodwill and deſire of the common good, and his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties ſeruice, you had well conſidered that the King of Spaine, not of any will or deſire, but through méere néede of the common danger and welfare, did make theſe warres, and brought his Campe there, and that through delaye of paiment, the Souldiours were through néede, forced to runne ſéeking of hearbes, and elſewhat, for their foode and liuing: the force of all which diſorder was not to be to the reproche of the king, nor the Chieftaines of his Campe, but to thoſe which were cauſers thereof, and that ought not preſently to be reuenged, with killing and murthering, but one ought to endure much, vppon hope of a good end of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16254:22"/>
manifolde miſchiefs and miſeries: the which would not only be pleaſing vnto vs, but promiſed that the king, and the illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Archeduke would be mindefull of it, and excuſe the ſame as the neceſſitie required. And it is wiſhed that all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which owe all ſuch ſeruice, to vſe the ſelfe ſame waye eyther through themſelues or their people, and in all mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie to ioyne their willing mindes and furtherances to our actions.</p>
                  <p>And whereas we haue from the beginning (to the common good) made our mindes knowne, publickly and priuately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared our goodwill, to the Earle of <hi>Brooke,</hi> by wordes, meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers and Letters. At laſt (after many great complaints, of the miſrule and had dealings of his men) wee receyued of him a Letter in Dutch, the contents whereof we ſcarce vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and yet by interpretation found them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what bitter, and eſtraunged to amity, we anſwered him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in Latin (which is common to all nations, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of all) that he would ſend vs the meaning of his Letter, with his minde, to the ende that we might the better an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere him, and to conuert his minde and ours to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſeruice, which we hoped he would haue doone: and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting certaine dayes his anſwer, there came dayly more complaints and outcryes to our eares, of the murthers, ſlaughters, and all manner of Barbarous cruelties doone to our Souldiors and others perſons, by the ſaid Earles cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feathers (or ſouldiours ſo called) to our great gréefe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, which all notwithſtanding we (ſtill expecting his anſwer) diſpiſed, and haue not any wayes conſented to any harme of his by worde or déede, vntill at laſt, by reaſon of the tumult of the whole campe of the chéefe captaines &amp; others, of all nations vppon theſe neuer heard cruelties, of ſlaying and murthering againſt the guiltleſſe perſons of our campe, by the Earles people, we concluded to ſend him our third writing, containing our diſpleaſure, of his foe-like actions, wondering that he anſwered vs not, declaring that it would be a great ſhame and diſhonour to the royall campe, to ſuffer ſuch indignitie to remaine vnpuniſhed, wherefore we reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, that he would puniſh and diſmiſſe all ſuch cockfeathers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16254:23"/>
and murtherers, or els deliuer them vp into the hands of the Iuſtices to puniſh them, and that for the reſt hee ſhould ſettle himſelfe to all amiable ſeruice. Theſe letters we gaue vnto a Spaniſh Colonel, cauſing him to take with him, ſouldiers and ordinaunce, ſuſpecting the Earles continuance of obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie, yet with charge, that comming to the Caſtle, he ſhould ſummon the Earle vpon the contents of the Letter, and in friendly ſort to ſpeake vnto him, and with all honour and reuerence to declare him our mindes: vpon the which if hee ſhould ſeeke any further delayes, make refuſall, or any ſhowe of enmity, that then the Colonel ſhould martial wiſe, forciblye take him, yet with ſuch condiction, that if in caſe the Earle ſhould bethinke himſelf better, and ſhould by déeds ſhew the ſame, that then his perſon, wife, children and his houſholde ſhoulde haue all their goods and heritages ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
                  <p>When now the Spaniſh Colonel, ſought by all friendly meanes to come to the Earles ſpeach, and to accompliſh the contents of the Letters, and that the Earle againe ſought diuers néedleſſe delayes, they betooke themſelues on both ſides to armes: wherby enſued, what in ſuch like tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aſſaults of angred ſouldiers by ſo many wrongs, is vſed to happen: yea often againſt their Commaunders will, the more becauſe his Campe was of many ſortes of peoples, whereof the greater part, yea the whole Campe was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encouraged by the barbarous cruelties, ſlaughters, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and damages ſuffered: which the Kings people eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be done by the counſaile of the neighbour countryes, with which they were in League.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ieſuits</note>There was a third ſort of people in the Campe, the which according to right and reaſon, diſcloſed, gaue and appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to euery one his actes, with the cauſes thereof, accuſing the Earle the more becauſe that for many yéeres hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelfe a defendour and vpholder of all ſedition, with chaunge of religion, not only ſetting the Countries of the Illuſtrous Prince at contention, but alſo himſelfe rayſde ſeditions, in the other common Landes, hauing euer ſince the wars, conſpired, conſulted and traded with the enemies
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16254:23"/>
of the commonwealths reſt, of the religion, and of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and they accompt the Authours and men of ſuch bad euents, to be more dangerous and damageable in a common wealth, then thoſe which through their inſtigation vnwit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinglye giue themſelues to armes, and ſo fall into like fault, inſomuch that the common opinion is, that therefore the ſaid Earle not onely, according to the lawe of armes, but alſo according to the lawe of God and man, hath receiued his rewarde according to his deſerts, and that others by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample will take warning, and the people be mooued to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: we notwithſtanding (according to our naturall kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) haue had compaſſion vppon his and the poore peoples miſhap, that they haue not followed good counſaile in time, and therefore haue wee related your honours the ſame at large, not that we will anſwere the fact, or that we deſire (in the leaſt point to haue the authoritie of the illuſtrious prince of <hi>Gulich</hi> or yours, to be deminiſhed (which we rather with all honour ſéeke to augment) but that we might in ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your wiſdomes, procure, that with the like ſorrowe they wil bewaile the anger of God, and the madneſſe of men, and to pray ſtedfaſtly, for that which is néedefull, for the good and quietneſſe of the commonwealth and the religion, and with diligence to foreſée therein, as néede requireth, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing alſo that you will interpret and publiſh the whole to the beſt: In the which we beſéeche God to ſtrengthen your Honors, and long to continue you in good eſtate. From <hi>Orſay</hi> the viii. of October 1598.</p>
                  <p>In this ſorte was the Earle of <hi>Brooke</hi> murthered in colde blood, and his death anſwered.</p>
                  <closer>Reade and Iudge.</closer>
               </div>
               <div type="list">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:16254:24"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>A Liſt of the troupes of men of warre,</hi> furniſhed by the Germaine Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Princes, in the defence of the Spanish <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and their bloudy and tyranicall enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> all ready begun in <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> and the Neighbour Countries.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Enry Duke of Browneſwick maketh out. 3000. horſemen, and 9000. footemen.</item>
                     <item>The Duke of Lunenburch. 1000. horſe and 2000. foote.</item>
                     <item>The Duke of Brandenburch Prince Elector. 2000. horſe and 4000. foote.</item>
                     <item>The Biſhopricke of Maghdenburch. 1000. horſe and 2000. foote.</item>
                     <item>The Duke of Saxony Prince Elector. 2000. horſe and 4000. foote.</item>
                     <item>Wirtzenburch. 1000. horſe and 4000. foote.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:16254:24"/>The Marqueſſe of Antzbach. 1000. horſe and 4000. foote.</item>
                     <item>The Count Palatine of the Rhyne. 1000. horſe and 4000. foote.</item>
                     <item>The Prouinciall Earle of Heſsen. 1000. horſe and 3000. foote.</item>
                     <item>The Count of Lippe. 500. horſe and 1000. foote.</item>
                     <item>In all 13500. horſe and 37000. foote.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>For the payment of theſe Souldiers ſhall be vſed the gathered contribution againſt the Turke.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
